Hi everybody,
Eric Artst here, your hopefully
helpful CIS133JS lecturer.
This week we are on
week three of our course
and I'm really excited
because we're diving
into functions and
comparisons this week.
Functions are a super
important part of
JavaScript. They allow
us to package various
types of behaviors that
define the workflows
and logical flows that
a program executes.
They define how the
program manipulates
data within the
state of the program.
and they allow us to
define reusable behavior
that we can export out
of one module and import
into another module and
use all over the place
and we'll go through a
quick example of that
during our demo today
and we're also going
to dive into comparisons
which a lot of
the a lot of the
comparison subjects in
JavaScript are relatively
straightforward.
We have equality operators
and other operators
that look a lot like
operators in other languages,
but there are some
nuances in JavaScript.
And the main nuances are
around coercion, which is where
you have two different
values that you're comparing
that are not of the same
type as defined by the type
of operator and javascript
will coerce one of the values
in these coercive equality
operations so that it
matches the type of the other
value and that can lead to
some confusing and sometimes
humorous results so we'll
talk about all that we'll
talk about value equality
and referential equality
so how javascript compares
primitives to objects is
quite different Objects are
compared by reference, so if
we're comparing two different
objects, we're looking at
whether those two objects
are defined at the same
location in the application's
memory state, whereas with
primitives, you are actually
comparing the values of
those primitives. we'll talk
about truthy and falsy rules
all values in JavaScript
can resolve to truthy or
falsy and as a result you can
use any JavaScript value
within an if statement or a
ternary operation or a loop
exit condition you don't have
to use boolean you can
use any JavaScript value
because all JavaScript values
will either resolve to truth
or false if they are placed
in within those contexts
we're also going to talk
about the assignment this
week because we're quickly
moving into some very
functional work in our assignment
and this week we're going
to create a program that
displays a html form with
an input a text input
field and the user will be
able to type in a username
into that field and find out
whether that username is
legal according to the
rules that have been defined
around the legality of that
username in that context.
So we're quickly getting
into some cool features
where we are putting inputs
into the document and we
are evaluating the text and
data that's been entered
into those inputs by users
and then we're performing
operations on that data
and displaying information
in response to various tests
that we apply to those
values so yeah this this
week's assignment is is going
to be pretty cool and I'll
give you some help with
some of the sort of runtime
environment nuances of the
browser document object
model and how forms work
and how event handlers work
within the DOM, but we'll
get to that in a minute.
So without further ado,
let's go ahead and jump in.
As always, I'm going
to use our example
file as my framework
for lecturing on this
topic, and if I bounce
back to our module
here and jump into
my lectures page here
hopefully we have a
link to the example here
maybe not maybe it's
in the overview silly
me I need to link it to the
overview but if you go to
our class repo you're going
to see these examples here
so under the examples folder
of the repo we're going
to see our week three functions
comparisons and I'll be
sure to link them going
forward in our overview doc
and I have grabbed this
example like we did last week
and I've pasted it into a
snippet in my chrome developer
tool so we can play around
with function definitions
So before we dive in
too much further as to
the various types of
functions and such,
let's talk about
reusability a little bit.
So I'm going to
run this snippet
here, our week three snippet.
And you can see that
it prints out some
output, just like our week
two one. but this week
I recognized that
the output's a little
hard to read sometimes
in the console because
it's just a stream of
output and it's hard to see
which function that output
came from so I wanted to define
a heading for each to
separate each function's
output from the other
function's output. And so I'm
printing out these little
headings here with five asterisks
and the name of the
function. You can see here we
have function forms demo,
and then we have a parameters
and returns demo, and
we have a strict versus
loose equality demo, and so
on and so forth. So these
are all different functions
that do completely different
things because they're
demonstrating different
aspects of our topics this
week, but they all need a
header. And we want to use
that same code repeatedly in
this program. And so rather
than repeating ourselves
by defining the same logic
flows in multiple places,
we are defining a single
reusable function that
I called header, and it
receives an argument called
label and prints out
that passed string in
addition to a couple new
lines and a few asterisks. So
it's printing out the label
that was passed to the
function, and it's using
the string template here
to print out a couple
new lines a few asterisks
and the label that was
passed in so let's look at
the parts of this function
here we have this is a
function declaration and
as a function declaration
this can be defined anywhere
in this module now for
clarity the function is defined
above where it's actually
referenced but there is
a visibility nuance to
functions in terms of where
they are available to use
within the program versus
where they are not available
to use and the function
declaration form of functions
which this one is this
highlighted header function
here this definition can
be placed anywhere in this
file and it will be made
available anywhere in the
program so in fact and this
is a this is a feature of
javascript called hoisting
and we talked about the var
keyword last week and how
it has a similar behavior in
that if you define a variable
using the var keyword
you can put that definition
of that variable at
the very bottom of your
program and then you can
refer to it and since
it isn't defined
hasn't been defined a
value yet it's going
to have an undefined
value until it has that
var statement assigning
value to it but
the variable itself is
available everywhere
in the program okay so
so yeah what's happening
here let's just put
a breakpoint here
and we're going to go
ahead and clear our
output and let's just
run this one more time.
And so I started
running the program and
it immediately, before
it even got to any
of the output, it has
printed out. We've
ended up stuck in
this breakpoint here.
I didn't, I don't think
I talked about the call
stack last week when we
were going through stuff,
but in the Chrome
developer tools, one of the
features is that we have
this call stack and you
can see that we are now
within a context called
the header this is the
header functions context
and then the the base
context is this anonymous
context here where we don't
have a defined function
wrapping this entire snippet
so we're just it's just
called anonymous by the
JavaScript runtime so if
I click on this anonymous
line right here it's showing
me that we've stopped we've
we've hit a breakpoint
in the header function on
line 99 but if I highlight
the line below it here
in the call stack I can
see that this is being
invoked from line 102 so you
can use the call stack to
sort of navigate around
within your running program
and you can see the data
that's available at each
level of the program and
there's a a set of values
that are available in these
various places so we have
right here we have selected
the anonymous scope
here where this header
function was first invoked
and if I look at this this
scope value right here well
scope is defining sort of
the geographical location
of this line of code that's
executing and it if we
expand this we could see
what values what variable
values are available within
this global scope and it's
a huge list because there's
a whole bunch of runtime
environment values that
are just available everywhere
in the browser context.
But if we bounce up to
header, and we're now looking
at two scopes here. So
we have our global scope,
which we looked at earlier,
that was in line 102.
But we also have a
local scope right here.
And this is also defining,
showing us something
about the context. So
I'll get to context in a
little bit. But we can
see that by defining this
label parameter for
this function, and I use
parameter and argument
kind of interchangeably,
so I hope that's not
confusing for you, but this
label parameter that's
part of this function,
you can see that it
has defined a variable
called label within the
scope of this function.
And in the developer
tools, we're able to see
what the value of that
variable is. So that's
super helpful. And as
we looked at last week,
you can just hover over a
given variable and Chrome
will helpfully show you
what the value of that
variable is, and I can also
type label here and hit
enter in the console, and
it'll show me what that value
is here. Now, this label
value is available here,
but if I bounce over to
the global scope here where
this function is being
invoked, and if I try that
same thing and type
label, well, it's going to
complain because label is
defined within the scope of
this header function, not
within the global scope.
So that can be a source of
confusion sometimes
in JavaScript.
But anyway, so what's
happening here is there were a
bunch of definitions in this
snippet that all got done.
And then we ended up on
line 102 and we're invoking
this header function. And
we're sending it function
forms demo as its parameter
value for the label to
assign to this label parameter.
and then within the function
we have a console dot
log that's using a string
template to print out a little
header above the function
output so we'll go ahead
and let this well actually
I'll leave this breakpoint
on because I want to run
it again okay so just remember
the call stack because
we have anonymous on line
102 and then we have header
on my 99 and let's just
allow the program to run to
the next spot and now we can
see that we're in line 105
of the program we're
calling this header function
with a completely different
string value to pass to the
label and here we're back
in if I highlight the header
scope within the call stack
I can see that the label
now has value of parameter
and returns demo so that's
just a quick demo of reusable
functions and showing
the function declaration
form of a function
and before I leave this
introduction behind
I'm going to go ahead and
close this and go back to
week one and I'm going to
show you this hoisting uh,
feature of the
function declaration.
So I can place this function
declaration at the very
bottom of this program. And
you can see that I'm
invoking the function above
where the function is
actually defined. I'm going to
go ahead and save the snippet
and let's go ahead and
run this. And hopefully
we're going to get the exact
same results as before in
that we are getting that
function is being invoked
successfully with its
different arguments or
parameter values past the label
and it is defined at the
very bottom of this module
but it's available throughout
the module so this is
a feature of the function
declaration form of creating
functions there's three
different ways that you
can define a function and
this function declaration
pattern which has been
around javascript from
the very beginning has
this hoisting capability
so these function declarations
they always follow
this format here we have
the word function followed
by the name of the
function and then we have
the arguments if there
are no arguments or
parameters, you just have
an empty set of parentheses
there, and then you have
the function body, which
is enclosed in curly
braces. So that's the format
of the function declaration
form of functions.
So let's go ahead and
look at our first demo,
which we invoke very,
I think it's the first
thing we invoke here, is
the function forms demo.
And we're going to go ahead and
start right here at the
very top and it looks like
when I try to define a
variable there it is a break
point it's actually putting
it here so I'm going to
actually drop it right here
the break point actually
let's do it here so we'll
do this okay so we have
a function called
function forms demo that's
demonstrating the three types
of function declarations so
I've just restarted the
snippet and we can see this
right here at the top we
have all three examples of
function forms here and
we already talked about
the function declaration
form which has the word
function, followed by
the name of the function,
followed by a set of
parentheses with an optional
list of arguments within
those parentheses.
What we didn't talk
about earlier with this
header function is the return
value. Now, this function
does not have a return
value. Well, actually, it
does have a return value.
Because this function doesn't
have an explicit return
statement inside of it it
returns undefined so when
you run this function if you
try to capture the output
or the return value of this
header function with whatever
label you passed into it
you're going to get undefined
as the return value so
undefined is the default
return value of a function
and in a function declaration
you have to use the return
value the return keyword
in order to return value so
in the case of this greek
declaration name function
this is a function
declaration form and it has an
explicit return value and it
returns a string value that's
generated from this string
template so it's returning
the value of this string
template as interpreted
given the name that was passed
to the function so let's
go ahead and put a breakpoint
here and a breakpoint
here and we can't really
put a breakpoint in this one
because of this fat arrow thing
now I can put a breakpoint
in this fat arrow function
but I need to do this
and I think there's a
way of doing this in
and I'm going to put an
explicit return statement
here and we'll come
back to this in a minute
okay so first of all we're
going to log the function
declaration we're sending
the same value to these three
functions eta is the name
in each case that we want
to use as the greeting and
when we invoke the greet
declaration function and I'm
going to go ahead and use
the step into function call
and we end up within this
function we can see the
name parameter is defined
as eta and then we're returning
a greeting of hello eta
using this string template
and we'll ahead and pass
over that and the return
value of greet declaration
is being passed to this
invocation of console.log now
let's go ahead and clear
this console out so we can
see exactly what happens here
we're not confused so I'm
going to step over because
we already ran greet
declaration we got back a
value of hello ada and when we
go ahead and allow the
console.log to execute with
that return value, we see
that it's logging out that
string that was returned from
the function declaration.
All right, so the next form
of defining a function are
these function expressions,
and this is where you
assign a function to a
variable, and so functions are
values in JavaScript so
functions are one of the major
value types in JavaScript
along with objects and strings
and the other primitives
the other object types of
functions are a value type
and so you can assign a
function to a variable here
so we actually have a variable
called greet expression
being invoked with that same
string of eta and let's go
ahead and step over here
over this console statement,
and we bounce right into
this function right here,
we can see a pretty similar
construct here in that
we have the word eta
that is being displayed
for our output. It's
being passed into the
name parameter, and
we're returning the same
template out of this
function expression called
greet expression. And
if we step over this, we
can see that we end up
we've run greet expression.
We have the string helloAda
back from it, and now
we're going to log that
value. And so I'm going to
allow the console.log to
execute, and we can see
that we got the same string.
Okay, and now that brings
us to the last of the three
function declaration
types, and these are arrow
functions, or aka, I called
it a fat arrow function to
begin with. there are no
skinny arrow functions in
JavaScript there's just these
fat arrow functions and they
are defined using this
interesting syntax here where
you have instead of having
a function keyword and
having a function name all
you have is this parenthesis
a set of parentheses
with an optional list of
arguments within them. You
have this fat arrow this equal
greater than symbol right
here and then you if you
have multiple lines of this
fat arrow function you're
gonna have to wrap them in
curly braces just like we
do with the other two forms
and we'll see what it looks
like when you don't do
that in a minute but I'm
gonna go ahead and hit my
resume execution and it looks
like it didn't stop at the
debugger that time so I
should have just stopped
there let's run it again our
call stack there it is
let's run this again okay so
I put a debugger statement
right here in this fat
arrow function. I was
hoping to see it stop there.
Oh, there it goes. Maybe I
forgot to save it. So I stuck
this debugger statement in
here. And so this is the
first statement within our
fat arrow function. And then
there's an explicit return
here, which is returning
the string template, same
thing as the prior to. And we
can see that this is going
to happen the same way. I'm
just going to step over
this debugger statement. And
then we're going to allow
the return statement to run
we exit out of the function
now we're in the console
.log and we're going to hit
over that and we end up with
one more hello ada printed
out on the console all right
so now what I want to do
is I want to go back to the
earlier form of this function
arrow function declaration
right here in which I
didn't have any curly braces
I only had this construct
right here where we have the
let me go ahead
and save this so we
don't have that same
confusion again here
and we'll let this we'll
let this run through because
we um we we stopped it
there so we're gonna we
made a change so we want
to go ahead and reset the
breakpoint here so I'm going
to run the program again
we're stopping out our
console.log we're invoking
greet arrow function and
let's see what happens here
so in this case we've got
a this function expression
arrow function has a
argument list and closed in
parentheses it's got our
fat arrow symbol and then
it's immediately displaying
a value and in this form
of the arrow function this
value here is the return
value so there's an implicit
return statement happening
here and so we're seeing
we're going to see the
same uh value point print
out so we have hello eta
hello eta those were from
the prior to and then when
we trace over this we
can see that this string
right here is the return
value of this arrow function
there's another difference
between arrow functions and
function expressions and
that's in terms of how scope
works and context works so
scope is the geographical
location of a given JavaScript
statement and the scope
of a statement defines the
visibility of variables
that that javascript statement
has available to it based
on its geographical location
within the program there's
another concept in
javascript called context and
that concerns the this keyword
this is a pointer to the
context of any function and
for function declarations
and function function
expressions, the context can be
set at the time that the
function is invoked. With
the fat arrow function, the
context is set by the enclosing
context from where the
arrow function is defined.
So we're going to get into
this a lot more later on,
I believe, in week six.
But I just want you to keep
those two ideas in your
head, that we have the idea
of context, which is the
data environment that's
accessible via the this keyword
within a function and then
we also have scope which
is sort of the set of
variables that are available
to a specific line of
JavaScript based on where that
line of JavaScript exists
and in this case we have
within this function forms
demo we've defined three
different functions here we
have a function declaration
called greet declaration
and then we have a function
expression assigned to the
greet expression constant
and then we have a fat arrow
function that's defined
to the greet arrow variable
and these three variables
are all visible within
this function forms demo
scope of this
function forms demo.
So hoisting, how does
hoisting work? We talked
about that earlier when
we moved the header
function, the declaration
of the header function to
the very bottom of the
file. This works exactly
the same when the function
is defined within a
function block of its
own, and here we have a
function called hoisted
that receives an argument,
and it returns hi of
the name passed in.
So if I pass over this
console log here, we're
invoking hoisted
invoked with an argument
of grace we're going to
see that it worked it
didn't crash even though
hoisted is defined
after its reference here
on line 17 because of
the behavior function
declarations it's possible
to declare your functions
at the bottom of
your module and they are
still hoisted they're
they're made visible from
the top of the module
down so that's an interesting
nuance of how Now,
function declarations work,
which is different from
function expressions and
arrow functions, both of
which do not hoist their
values, except if we defined
that function with a var,
okay? Because we already
talked last week about
VARs and how VARs hoist
their values, and that
is another example of how
this idea of hoisting works,
that if you define a VAR
variable, its existence
and value assigned to it
at the time that it is
created will be hoisted to
the top of whatever scope
that variable is running
in and let's go ahead and
let's go ahead and try that
real quick here so we'll
do another hoisting value
but we're going to do a
var of hoisted fat arrow
and I'm going to say it's
going to equal to a fat
arrow function that just
says it's just going to say
hoisted okay and then we're
going to do the same thing
here we're going to do
console dot log of hoisted
fat arrow and hopefully
this is going to work if it
doesn't it's because I've
forgotten how assignments to
hoisted variables actually
work okay so let's go ahead
and it's not letting me
put a breakpoint in here
so we're just going to
go ahead and run this and
hopefully it's not going
to crash so let's clear the
output and run it again looks
like it didn't crash okay
interesting so it didn't
crash it did not crash but
because the assignment to
this var occurred after its
reference this assignment
never happened before the
reference to hoisted fat
arrow was done so that's
how hoisting works with vars
and that the availability
of that variable is hoisted
to the top of the scope
but the actual value assigned
to it doesn't come into
being until that line of
code is actually run and
so if we moved this over
above our invocation of it.
Well, hopefully we're going
to see the results I'm
predicting now, which is that
it's printing out hoisted
fat arrow. Oh, so look at
what's going on here. So when
I did console.log of hoisted
fat arrow, I just typed
in, I typed in hoisted fat
arrow, and look what it
printed out. It printed out
the actual signature of that
arrow function instead of
actually printing out the
return value. Now, was this
function invoked in this
case on line 23 when I tried
to do this ad hoc demo that
failed it was not so what
we got instead was we got
the the value of this
variable was printed out via
this console dot log and the
value of this variable is
a function that returns
the string hoisted but the
function wasn't actually
invoked so if we want to have
what we what I had intended
here I'm gonna save this
let's try it one more time and
run this and we'll see here
actually just do that again
and yeah there it is so
we actually invoke the function
instead of just printing
out the value of this
hoisted fat hour so okay all
right so we talked briefly
already about the fact
that we have parameters and
return values and functions
and so we've kind of covered
that already but we're
going to go ahead and breeze
through it real quickly here
so with our demo script
here we're going to go ahead
and run it and now we're
in the we did our function
forms demo already now
we're in the parameters and
returns demo this function
defines has a function declaration
at the top of it where
a function called make
greeting is defined, but we
have some new interesting
syntax sugar here with our
parameter list, and we have
some default values that
have been assigned to these
two parameters. so the default
value of name if it's not
specified in the invocation
of the function is going
to be friend and the default
value of the punctuation
argument is going to be a
exclamation point or bang
symbol and so we can see some
examples here of how when
we invoke this make greeting
function without arguments
we're getting some default
values filled in okay
so when we call make greeting
without any parameters
passed to it the parameter
defaults were applied within
the parameter block here
and then we get hello friend
per the definition of this
parameter list now if we
only supply one of the
arguments so we just apply the
first one supply the first
one well we get hello Sam
with an exclamation point so
now we have defined Sam as
the first parameter value
to pass in but we didn't
bother to define the punctuation
argument and so we're
sticking with the exclamation
point but now we have a
explicit value of the name
parameter and then here's
the full fully expressed
invocation of make greedy in
which case we have both of
the arguments defined and
we're seeing an output of
hello sam question mark because
we defined both the first
parameter and the second
parameter and so both those
overrides were applied
okay so um if we want to
create a well let's let's keep
let's stick to the script
here so we have another
function here which is our
min max function and we are
passing to this minmax function
an arguments parameter.
And this is demonstrating
that we can pass
various types of
objects to a function.
It doesn't have to be just
a primitive. It could be an
object or any JavaScript
value. and so this function
minmax is defined with a
numbers argument and it's
returning an object here
that it's sort of defining on
the fly here and what it's
doing is it's passing in an
object
with a property of min,
and the property of min is
being assigned the result
of calling math.min with a
set of arguments, and the
max is also being defined
to math.max. Now let's see
how math, what does math
.min, how does math.min work?
So if I type math.min, we
can see that the function
signature has a, it's like
an ellipsis with a set of
values. So if I type one,
two, and three of math.min,
I get one. So that makes
sense. And if I type math
.max of one, two, three,
I get three. But what if
I did this? What if I did
math.min of an array of 1,
2, 3, what happened there?
Well, we got the infamous
not a number result
from math.min, and so
I guess this math.min
browser execution context
function and object when it
receives an argument that
isn't a number and if I did
this math.min of let's say
if I did a string of high
there let's see what happens
there well that's another
nan not a number so the way
this function is defined if
it receives an argument
that is not an actual number
it rejects it essentially
returns a not a number value
what if I did this math
dot min of hi there
and one well it's
still rejecting it okay
because I'm passing
in some random strings
but now let's look at a
little bit of coercion
here so I do math dot
min of one two three
I'm not sure what's
going to happen here
But yeah, our helpful
preview is showing that
if I pass three strings
to this function as
the function arguments,
what's it doing here?
It is converting these
strings to numbers and
then printing out the
smallest of the numbers as
converted from these
strings. So this is this idea
of coercion, where
JavaScript will helpfully
coerce a value from one
type to another in order
to try to get a result
that it thinks you want.
And, of course, the problem
with assuming things is
that often our assumptions
are incorrect, and so
sometimes this can lead to
confusions around programs.
But let's go back to
this syntax right here
because we kind of got on a
little tangent there about
these different variations
of math.min and math.max
and how they handle
different arguments. Now we
established that if we
invoke math.min with an array
argument that it refuses
to deal with that. It's
not a number. It's an
array. It's an object. So it
returns and not a number.
But in here, in this function
here, we are deploying
this expansion operator.
So how does this work? So
if we pass an array, if we
define an array, and then
we invoke a function and we
prefix the array argument
with this three dots, it's
not an ellipsis, it's actually
three separate periods.
what javascript is going
to do is it's going to
take that array and it's
going to break those
elements of the array apart
into separate arguments
and then it's going
to invoke the function
with those very arguments
from the array so that's
what this is doing
right here and let's see
if we do this let's say
test equals one and two
and let's do console.log
of test. I'm not sure
what's going to happen
here. So it printed out
the array.
But if I do this, console
.log of test with three
dots in front of it, we get
a slightly different result
here. So what happened
here is in this case, it
printed out the array
representation of the test
variable but in this case
when we prefix the variable
name with three dots
console dot log is actually
printing out it those those
two values were separated
into multiple arguments
because that's how console
dot log works if I do
console dot log of hi there
class and I hit enter
hopefully I type that right
yes I did I get hi there
class if I do console log of
an array hi there class I
get a printout of the array
representation of that and
then let's just go ahead
and grab this last thing
I'm going to go ahead and
put that those three dots
right in front of this
array constant see what
happens now and now we're back
to this so you can apply
this three dot pattern to
any array and when you
invoke a function and you
prefix and an array argument
value that you pass to the
function with three periods
it's going to expand
those values into separate
arguments to pass to that
function. That's exactly
what's going on here. Okay.
All right. So what else
is going on? So we've
got a, um, we've got this
return value here. And
I think what I want to
do, let's do this. So
let's do const min max
result equal, and then
we'll go ahead and grab
this invocation here
and we'll put it here and
then we're going to go
ahead and put our min
max result that I want to
see these separate
values and what they what
they end up being I'm
going to go ahead and hit a
breakpoint right here
and I already saved this
let's just refresh this
page make sure we're not
running into serious
confusion when we invoke
this so I'm going to
go ahead and invoke
this function and we're
going to stop at 939 stopping
here do it due to a error
maybe it's because I
left a debug statement
in there let's go ahead
and keep moving here
okay here we go so we're
going to invoke min max
with an array and we're
going to assign it to this
constant okay so what is
in this constant well this
is an object that has two
keys it's got a max key
and a min key and so that
was those were produced by
this return statement here
which we created an object
with a key of min and
a key of max with the
pointing to the values that
were return from these two
math functions and then
what what are we doing here
so what we're doing here
is on line 41 is we're
we're doing an assignment
to two different variables
and we have this
interesting little
curly bracket
construct right here
and this is very related
to the this array explosion
operator of this triple
period here and that what's
happening with this is that
when you make an assignment
where the right hand
value in the assignment is
an object and then on the
left side of the equal
sign you have keywords that
are defined in that object
it defines new variables
so we have a min variable
right now and we have a
max variable we actually
have three variables we
have the min max result that
was returned and then we
performed an assignment in
which we exploded the keys
of this object out into
some other variables. Now
let's see if I can do this.
I'm just going to do
an expression here.
I'm going to wrap this
in parens so I can
avoid having to actually
define a constant.
So let's do min and
max and hello and
we're going to say
equals min max result.
Let's see what happens here.
Okay, so what happened?
So we defined, we
tried to find min max
and hello. Okay, so
what's min right now? Min
is one, we established
that max is nine.
And what about hello?
Well, hello is undefined.
Why is hello to undefined?
Because there's no key
called hello in the min max
result value this object
and so it just assigns
undefined in this case so this
is a shortcut in javascript
that you can use to pull
object values out of an
object if you want to get
them into a separate variable
and so that was the
parameters and returns demo
we need to keep moving
all right so let's
go to strict versus
loose equality demo
all right now this is
one of the most crazy and
controversial aspects of
javascript a lot of people think
that this is one of the
examples of why javascript
is weird and bad and that
has these coercions so
the triple equal operator
is a compares the types of
the two values first and
if the types are different
types it returns it
yields a false so it first
checks the types of the two
values and returns false if
the types are different
it then if the types are
the same it then goes on to
the actual values in those
two values and it compares
those okay so in this
case we have console dot
log of one triple equal one
and we're getting a true
because these two numbers
are both primitives they're
both number primitives
and they have the same
value so they're getting
a true now if I do a console
dot log of the number
one compared to the
string of one I get false
because the triple equal
starts with the type
and then it looks at the
values and so in this
case the types are different
one's a number one's
a string and so it
just returns a false in
this case and the triple
equal there's a lot of
like linters and I don't
know if you've um I
think we do have a
JavaScript formatter in this.
It's a famous, famous project.
Okay, so this is a static
code analyzer that is a
incredibly useful tool to
have in any kind of JavaScript
project, and it makes
sure that you don't have
syntax problems in your code.
So instead of allowing the
code to be compiled first and
then find out that there's
a syntax error in it at
runtime, we are actually
doing a static analysis of the
code using this tool. And
in many ESLint definitions,
that ESLint is super
flexible. You can define
any kind of rules you
want in it. It has a
bunch of built-in rules
and has these suggestions
and standard things
and things like that.
But in many projects,
the use of the
double equal operator
is prohibited.
And most of the projects
that I work on professionally
have this rule in
place, that you're not
allowed to use the double
equal. It's just too
confusing. Because in this
case, I have two values.
One is a number, one
is a string. and we're
going to see that
javascript says yeah this
is the same these are
these are the same
the number one is the same
as the string one but that's
not really true right there
are different types now
you may be wanting to use a
double equal operator there
may be a situation in your
code and in fact our our
our you don't know JS program
they are he's his name is
his name is Kyle nice my
kids I have a kid named Kyle
So let's see,
chapter two, this is
where he's talking
about this stuff.
Okay, so he is careful to
indicate in his write-up
of the double equal operator
that it's not evil, that
it's a feature of JavaScript.
Okay.
So in most cases, the
double equal works
exactly the same as
the triple equal.
In cases where you're
comparing two different values
of the same type, they
work the same. But we do
have this coercion behavior
in the double equal
operator and I forget where
he talks about this the
the case of never using
it versus using it smartly
I'm not very smart so I
never use the coercive value
of the equality operator.
He's kind of dancing about
it right here because we
do use coercive values
even if you outlaw the use
of coercive comparisons
using the double equal.
If you're using any of the
greater than, less than,
greater than equal, etc.
comparison operators,
those coerce. So
there is coercion
going on in JavaScript.
And he's saying that
the wiser approach is
not to avoid coercive
comparisons, but to
embrace and learn
their ins and outs. And
that's very true. He's
very right about that.
However, every program
project that I've
worked on in the last
15 years has outlawed
the use of this double
-equal operator just
because of these points
of confusion, okay?
So there's, and
there's some of this
weird, these weird
JavaScript quirks.
They're really all in
the neighborhood of
this coercion behavior.
So here we have
console dot log of null
equal equal undefined.
That yielded true. So if I do
null equal equal undefined,
that's a little
confusing, right?
These are both being coerced
into a boolean value if
I do null equal equal
equal undefined it's false
because null and undefined
are two different types and
so that they are um that
yields a false in that case
okay so we see right here we
have referential comparison
of different arrays so
if we have a comparison
of the array constant one
two three and really I think
in a way it's easier just
to put these directly into
the console so that we're
not kind of viewing it
through the lens of console
dot log but if I define an
array containing the values
one two and three and I
do a triple equal comparison
to another array of one
two three now you might
expect this to be true but
these are two completely
different objects in memory
so the one on the left is
one object the one on the
right is another object and
they are both arrays they're
both a type of object but
they're different arrays
and so in the case of
objects the triple equal
operator does a comparison
by reference and I believe
it's the same for the double
equal operator in this
case but let's let's just
see what happens here so if
I did use the double equal
operator it's behaving the
same as the triple equal
operator in this case okay
so how if I did want to
define to look at two
different objects and see
if they're it's actually
the same object in memory,
and there are legitimate
cases to do that, what
I can do is I can define
a variable. So here I'm
going to find a constant a.
I'm assigning this array
to it, and then I'm
assigning a new variable
b to be the value of
a. So now they're both
pointing to the same
location in memory
where this original
array lives in, and
so when I do a console
.log of a triple
equal b, it's true.
Both of these values
on either side of
the triple equal
operator are the same
object, and so it's
going to be true.
We have quirks. We already
talked about this not-a
-number quirk, where if you
try to compare not-a-number
to not-a-number, you get
false okay that's a little
confusing and then because
of this quirk in the original
definition of how not a
number behaves with respect
to equality operators well
javascript at some point
we had to define a actual
method called is nan on
the number class in order
to perform this accurately
so if I do an nan triple
equal nan don't do that
because it's never going to
resolve to true but so let's
say this let's do this um
why do we care about this
so let's say if I do a min
of math.min of 1, 2, James,
and I want to see if that
produced a not a number,
well, that says false.
Okay, so we invoked math.min
with nonsensical arguments,
and we got a not a number
back, and my code may
want to check that return
value to make sure we didn't
get some kind of weird
value that we didn't expect.
Well,
we can't use the triple
equal operator, but
we can use the number
.isNAN for this purpose.
number dot is nan of that
same function that we
invoked earlier and in
this case we're getting
true so this is how you
can make sure that what
you're getting back is
actually a number not a
not a number okay all
right let's move on so uh
truthy falsy okay so we
have uh the idea that
values in javascript can be
truthy or falsy any value
is either truthy or falsy
and why is a value truthy
or falsy well it sort of
depends on the type of
the value and so in this
first example here we're
doing an if then and we're
using a empty string as our
if test and we can see
that that's a falsy value
because it's we're ending
up in the else clause here
here's another example
okay so here's a string
containing the string character
of zero and we're using
that to test in an if and
we're getting a truthy
value out of that okay but
what if we did this if zero
console dot log truth
truthy else console dot log
all c what do you think
is going to happen an
uncaught exception if zero
console dot log truthy
I need a semicolon
there. Sorry about that.
Let's try that. Okay,
so what happened there?
So
the zero is a falsy
value, the numeric
zero, but not a
string zero. So this
is one of these
JavaScript quirks.
Any kind of object value
type, such as an array, is
going to be truthy. that's
easy and then we have these
what's this demonstrating
that we can do a oh this is
the ternary operator okay so
this is sort of a shortcut
if then statement so we
have a age defined as the
number 20 and then we're
going to assign the variable
status the value of this
ternary expression in which
we are comparing age is
greater than equal to 18 and
if it's greater than equal
to 18 we're going to put
adult as the status otherwise
we're going to put minor
as the status so how does
this work so it indeed
compared the age to 18 and
then it assigned because this
is it evaluates to true,
as we would expect, it's
assigning the value adult.
So this is just a shortcut
if statement. But getting
back to our JavaScript quirks,
let's just grab this little
expression right here.
This is where this stuff
can get a little bit tricky.
Because these greater than
and greater than or equal
operators they perform
coercion so if I did this so
what's happening there is
I changed that comparison
value to a string of 18 and
in this case it converted
the 18 into the number
18 and then perform the
comparison so as you see we
can't get away from this coercion
problem issue. And I think
like, I'm pretty sure
that the math function,
the math, the math object
has just a ton of useful
functions. And I thought maybe
there'd be a greater than,
but some of the, some of
the math libraries define
different actual explicit
values to look at perform
non-coercive comparisons
here but it's not it's not
present here in the math
function okay what if I did
this let's pull that up so
what happened there so that
was that yielded a falsie
a false value when I
compared the number eight uh
the number 20 so because
age has 20 in it I compared
20 to the string 18 boof
um what is 18 boof well
it's a it's I'm pretty sure
that converts coerced into
a not a number and so if
I did this age is greater
than or equal to not a
number question mark adult
and then sure enough,
that's what happened
there, is that 18 boof
string was coerced into
a not a number object.
So is not a number 18
boof is not a number.
Oh, it's a number, sorry
not math oh so 18 booth is
is not a nan hmm interesting
all right well um what if
I did number of 18 booth I
think number is a constructor
it returned not a number
I'm really confused oh
anyway I digress we're
talking about the ternary
operator it's a
shortcut for an if then
statement all right so
all right so we've we've
kind of run through our
javascript topics thank
you for sticking with
me this long and now I
want to jump into our
assignment for this week
So we have an assignment,
which I believe
I may have actually
dropped into this
already. I don't
think I did already.
So the assignment is that
we're going to create
a username validator.
And I don't think I
actually pasted this in
yet to my thing. Let's go
ahead and copy this and
drop it in right now.
So that is the assignment.
Okay, so this week's
assignment, according to how I
wrote this thing up a week or
so ago, is that we are
going to create a username
validator. So write a
function that checks whether a
username meets a set of rules
and display pass-fail feedback
for each individual rule
in the DOM with no hard
-coded results in the HTML.
and so there's a set of
specific rules that we're
going to use in order to verify
that our username is valid
and there's five of them
and there's some suggestions
on how to do this and some
suggestions around tests
that you can create and but
what we want to do is we
want to create a cool little
HTML form for this okay so
let me close these tabs to
the right and let's let's
let's get out of this whole
debugging nonsense here and
let's look at my demo that
I made okay so um so I
didn't solve this problem yet
this this uh problem of
iterating through a series of
uh validation functions
and determining which one's
passed and which one's failed
and displaying the output
so that's part of your
assignment that you have to
complete but you what this
week's example code has some
of this stuff already here
so that's kind of helpful
but what I want to go over
with you right now is some
of the information that
you're going to need in order
to build this program because
what we want is we want
a little web page that has
a input box and some way
of typing data, some way of
submitting the typed string
to a function that will
evaluate whether this string
that was submitted is actually
a valid username according
to the rules that have
been placed upon us, okay?
All right, so So I'll
show you how my program
works, and this program
is fairly silly.
It's just a little
test harness, okay?
So I have to find an
HTML form here that has
an input field, and it
has a submit button.
and if I type james and
hit enter then it's just
doing a console log of
that string that was
entered in the value now
you didn't see my mouse
I don't know if you saw
where my mouse was but
james is very awesome and
let's go ahead and hit enter
so I'm not pressing the
click me button I'm just
hitting enter okay and so
this is a a feature of the
document object model within
a browser that there is a
specific type of HTML tag
called form and the form
tag allows you to create
a form that could have one
field in it or could have
a bunch of fields in it and
the form can have a submit
behavior so submitting a
form is like you've got a
bunch of information that
you filled out in the form
and you want to send it
somewhere and so that's what
a form submit is is that
you're taking information
that is contained in the
fields of the form and you're
submitting it maybe to a
server somewhere to create
a new login for somebody.
And forms have a behavior
in which when the user
hits the enter key within
a text field it's going to
cause the form to be
submitted. Now you can also
submit a form using a submit
button. So that's what this
button is. It's a button
with the type of submit.
And so if I click this,
let's put an exclamation
point here so we can keep
track of what we're doing.
All right. So here's the
James is very awesome bang
string. And if I click
this button, I'm getting
two exclamation points.
You know what? I think this
one is confusingly added
so let's let's do this
sorry about that because my
console dot log is actually
putting that exclamation
point in there okay so
I put two pounds and I
clicked click me and it's
printing out the string
that was passed into this
form and it puts a exclamation
point at the end of
the string okay so let's
first look at the markup
that I defined here okay
so what I set up was a form
it's in our handy
app div wrapper that
we've used in all of
our projects so far
and within the app div
wrapper I put in a h1 event
handlers heading and then
I have my form okay and
the form has an ID and the
the ID lets me retrieve
the form element using
the document query I think
it's document this is
find a document dot query
selector of pound
username form and
that gave us a link to
that form dom element
okay so I put an ID
in the form so I can
get to it easily from
my script using the
query selector here.
And what else is
here? So the form
tag is wrapping an input field.
The type of this
input field is text so
if we go to our
trusty mdn text input
page it's a basic
single line text field
now inputs have all sorts
of different types that
you can put in which is
kind of cool And some
of these inputs have very,
very special rendering
expressions, like a
password field, for example,
includes the feature of
blotting out the password.
Okay, so here's a
password field, and
when I type in the password
field, it masks my information.
So there's lots of
different types of inputs
that you can define in
browsers, and I'm sure
in the future there will be
more types of inputs, like
there's a date input type,
and it renders a, when
you do input of type of
date, it gives you a little
date picker, pops up a
little calendar this is this
is a browser specific
expression of how a calendar
picker works is this is how
Chrome does it and this is
influenced by the locale
that my machine is set to so
if I was if my machine was
set to work with a different
language from US English
the calendar would look
a little different from how
it looks right here just
by means of putting in
this type equal date but in
this case we're just using
a simple text field for
input so we're using type
equal text and by default if
you do an input with no type
it's a text field I have
my handy ID here so I can
get to it if I need to I
have a name attribute so
how this works in forums is
that the name attribute
becomes an element that is
expressed within the collection
of fields that are sent to
a back-end server via the
default form behavior. So
if I didn't have a certain
element in my script that
prevents the default form
handling, we would end up having
a submission of my value
to a server and in fact
let me go ahead and mess and
break this a little bit so
go to my app.js file here
I'm going to drag my Visual
Studio now I sternly warned
you guys not to use copilot
in your text editor due to
academic honesty issues,
but it's super helpful.
Um, so you may see
a little copilot
stuff because I do
use copilot, um,
truth be told. Um, so
this is my program right
here. So here's the
inner HTML definition of,
I grabbed the, um, the
form the appdiv and that's
defined by default for
our project and then
I use this string template
to create the markup
And I inserted that
markup into the
innerHTML of this app
element. So this markup
here is being dumped
into this app div.
Okay, so how am I wiring
all this up? All right,
so what I'm doing is after
I define the form And I
place it into the DOM by
assigning this string template
to this inner HTML value.
And I'm going to put
this example up in our
example area of our project.
And I don't know if
I talked about this
before. I don't think
I did, actually.
Let's go to my JavaScript
repo real quick.
because I wanted to
because I am going to be
updating this repo as
we go over the course
of this term because
this is actually the
first time I've taught
this javascript class
using this format that I'm
making up as I go along
essentially so um you
know there are a set of
examples in this repo of
mine for our class and I
just added this week three
functions comparisons
example to our example folder.
And this is the snippet
that I was messing around
with during the beginning
of my lecture. I have not
put in a week three form
handling example yet, but
I'm going to do it. It's just
not there yet. I'm going
to do that right after I
finish this lecture okay
but when you cloned your
repository initially and you
created a new repository using
this repository as a template
and you brought it down
to your local machine I
haven't defined this example
yet and so it's not there
on your local machine you
know I mean if you visit
my webpage here this repo
on public this public
repository you'll see it as soon
as I put it up but it's
not in your local folder so
if you want to grab updates
to the project there is I
believe there's some
instructions in here which I hope
I put okay so it's in read
me and it's this heading
called setting up to receive
course updates and this
is a little bit of git
stuff you can kind of see
how this works but you begin
by adding a remote to my
public repository that you
use to create your personal
copy of this repo and then
once you've added my repo
as a remote called template.
So in Git, let's see,
I just got to be careful
here. I've got lots
of stuff going on on
this computer and I want
to make sure I'm not
leaking my work to you
by accident. I'm just
popping open a new
terminal here. Okay,
so if I go to source,
Now let's go to slash
cocc.js slash course.
Okay, if I do a git remote,
I've only got one remote
to find because this
is the, I have a local
clone of my cocc.js repo on
my machine. and origin is
defined by default in a
git repo and that refers
to the repository that
you initially cloned the
local copy from. It's called
origin and in this case
we're defining a second
remote called template.
Okay so you just have
to do this once and then
when you do git remote
and hit enter you'll
actually see two remotes
you'll see origin and template
and then to reach
retrieve the templates
whenever you feel like
fetching some updates you
can just run this you
do get fetch template so
what that's doing get
fetched pulls the current
state of this remote
repository to your local get
repository on your machine. And
then I'm doing
this merge command.
This is a kind of a
complicated merge command.
Don't worry too much
about it. But what this
is doing is it's saying
that I'm going to
merge the main branch
of the template remote.
This is to make sure that we
don't have any messy merge
conflicts because of the
way that we've instantiated
these repos when we've copied
them to our github account
we use that template
feature and so this flag
prevents there from being
weird merge conflicts and then
this thing this x there is
basically saying when there's
a merge conflict just use
the upstream template remote
that's the source of truth
so we're not gonna have
a merge conflict in files
that are defined in my local
machine and are also
defining those remote so it
prevents her from being any
merge conflicts and then this
last thing is just a little
kind of a message flag that
you can put into a merge
command so that it doesn't
create the full screen usually
a vim editor to edit your
commit description so yeah
it's a little convoluted
but this is how you can grab
updates so if you want to
pull the new example that
I'm going to post after I
finish this lecture showing
this form handling stuff
this is how you can pull it
down to your local computer
and have it there or you can
just visit my my repo and
see it there okay so I got
I got really off track here
going back to my little
program I've defined a form
that has a single text
input. And there's some
little stuff in here
that I should probably
document what all these
attributes are doing.
But I'm going to leave
that off for now. And
the important thing is
that there's an input
with type text, and it
has a name of username.
And then there's a
button, a submit button,
that has the caption
click me right there.
and maybe we can make
this a little smarter
that's better okay so
it checks the username
probably don't need
an exclamation point
there okay all right
let's get rid of that
confusing bang there because
that was confusing me
five minutes after I wrote
this code okay so I type
in Eric and I hit enter and
I get hello Eric so this
submit button I can click
it and that'll cause
the value to be submitted
or I can just hit enter in
this text field and that'll
cause the form to be
submitted as well all right
now how am I wiring up this
code that's causing that
console to be displayed
Well,
I'm grabbing the form
element using its ID,
and then I'm using this
invocation of addEventListener
method on that DOM
element, and I'm
creating a submit handler
for this form and you
can see that there's
an event passed to this
submit handler this
argument now what kind of
what kind of function
definition is this exactly
if we go back to our
different types this
is actually a function
expression it's an
anonymous function expression
there's no name here
now I could put a name on
it if I wanted to that's
allowed this would
be the username form
handler thank you co-pilot
okay and so I am invoking
ad event listener there's
a helpful description
of what this function
does courtesy of MDN.
The name of the event that
I'm handling is submit.
And then I pass a value
to the second argument of
this function, which is a
function. So I'm passing a
function to this addEventListener
function. This is
the function that's going
to be invoked once a submit
event occurs with this
form. okay let's go ahead
and I've got this enticing
event prevent default
method and so what is event
well event is a object type
in the browser runtime
environment mdn event object
it's a very widely available
there's a whole ton
of different types of events
one of which is a submit
event okay so defines the
object used to represent
HTML form submit event
okay and it has some
documentation here on our
beloved MDN website and that
event object has a method
called prevent default let's
go ahead and put a console
.log here of form submit
and we're going to pass
the event and that's going
to cause my browser to
refresh here so sally is
my name and I'm going
to hit enter and so I'm
getting all the same
information here but now it's
logging out this event
object that's being passed
in and this event object
has a bunch of properties
okay so the target is
the the form element and
I'm not sure what submitter
does exactly default
prevented is true so that
means that it is not by
calling this method
prevent default preventing
the default browser behavior
of a form submission
from occurring at all
now what is that default
behavior so let's go ahead
and comment out event up
prevent default and let's
see what happens here
okay all right so this is
going to be um margaret
and we're going
to hit enter what
happened there what
was the default
behavior of this
event handler for
the form let's try
this again let's
just go ahead and
revise the
URL again, margarit.
Note, what I have right here
is I have the
localhost domain and
the port of our
starter project.
I'm going to go ahead
and hit the button.
What just happened here?
Why didn't I get a console?
that's weird let's try
it again what why is this
stuff showing up in the
URL what's this username
thing well we know Margaret
we know where that came
from because we type the
word Margaret what if
I type Jim and hit enter
well now we're getting
username equal Jim But what
is this URL right here?
Well have you ever gone to
a website that has query
params where you're doing
a search for something
and you've got a bunch of
query params and I've been
looking for Logitech mice
on my on eBay because my
my Logitech trackball
is has given up
the ghost so if I type
Logitech trackball
or something like that
and hit enter in eBay, I
get something kind of
similar here. I get a new
path here and there's
this question mark
separator here and then I
get something very similar
where I've got the
text I entered in this
field here and then I've
got some other stuff
that it threw up there
but it all ended up in
the browser and then
if I if I bookmark this
page and I put it in my
trusty CoCCJ CoCC folder and I
hit done okay so now I
bookmark this and now what if
I go back to this and I hit
enter the bookmark star went
away look at that and now
I've got this this other
URL here if I click here now
I'm back to the eBay homepage
and I've got a clean URL
without any query params
so what's happening here
is this query param pattern
is ubiquitous in the internet
it's been here forever
since the beginning of browsers
and if you want to perform
a search on any kind of
website you will often end
up seeing these search
parameters show up in your URL.
And remember I
bookmarked that search
result in eBay?
Well if I go here
and I go to my
bookmark and I click it
it's restoring the search
that I entered complete
with the typo that I
entered in the field
name here okay so this is
a uh a url that includes
search params or aka
query params and these
are um there's a there's
always a question mark
after the path and then
there are a series of
key value pairs where the
key is on the left side of
the equal and the value is
on the right side of the
equal. And then if there are
multiple of these, you're
going to see these ampersands
separating them. So in this
case, it looks like we have
three different key value
pairs. We have NKW and FROM
and TREXID, whatever that
is, whatever eBay uses that
for. But we can use that
in our program here as
well. So let's say I was
trying to evaluate Sally
again and I hit enter
and I want to bookmark
this and put it in my
COCC folder. And then
I'm going to do it again,
but I'm going to type
James instead and do that.
And now I can bookmark that.
Okay. Now we're not going
to see a whole lot here
because I don't have any
kind of like parsing of this
URL happening it's all
code that you have to write
in order to wire this type
of behavior up that we
saw in that eBay website
where when I restored that
Logitech mouse search bookmark
I got the field filled
in with my typo written
search query that I typed
in eBay okay but let's
go back back to and these
are both bookmarks so this
one is username equal Sally
and this one is username
equal James okay so let's
let's go ahead and see
what's going on here because
it's kind of interesting
how this stuff works now
forms are super powerful
elements in JavaScript and
the dom okay and you
notice that we have a we
commented out event dot
prevent default so the default
behavior of an HTML form
in the browser is that when
you submit the value of
that form, it's going to
perform a GET request to
the server that served that
page, and each field of
that form is going to be
represented by a key value
pair in that search string that
gets created. So that's
the default behavior of a
form is that it performs a
get request to the server
and it reloads the browser
with that new URL that it
constructs from the default
path that was already
there and the set of form
values. okay so here we have
a input with a name of user
name which is represented
right here and when I hit
when I type in Jane and
I hit enter now before
when we were preventing the
default behavior we were
seeing some console action
right but in this case we're
seeing that the page kind
of refreshes really quickly
and then the browser URL
gets replaced with the
former URL with a question
mark and a single search
key value pair of username
equals J. So username came
from the name of this field
that I entered as an
attribute of the input field.
And the value came from
the value that the user
actually entered. In
this case, it was Jane.
Okay.
But why did we see any console
output. Well, the reason
we didn't see any console
output, maybe it did happen,
but what happened was
when we submitted the form
and we are allowing the
default behavior of the browser
form element to be invoked,
it refreshes the page with
a new URL consisting of
that original path with the
search query parameters
appended to it. So if we want
to see that console action
that we were seeing before,
we got to set up a
little flag for the
console. And I think
I always forget where
it is when I have
the console stuff.
So I hit this gear icon here,
and I am going to say keep log.
Okay, and let's close it
again. So I just set up
my console so that it's
going to retain the logs in
between page load transitions
and so I'm going to
once again type let's type
Janie this time and hit
enter all right so now we're
seeing the same behavior
where the screen refresh
we had a hard reload
of the web page we had a
new key value pair appended
to the URL after the
question mark we have our
new value that I entered
in the field of Janie we
have the old value of
username equal Janie and now
we're seeing that what was
happening here was those
console logs were actually
firing but the browser
refreshed so darn quick
that we didn't even see
it okay and here chrome
is giving us a helpful
little navigated to indicator
here which I think it
only prints that when
you have that keep log
setting so if I um joseph
it doesn't print it if
you're not doing blog but
when you use keep log it
prints it out so you kind
of keep track of where
it's going and then you
can even keep testing this
okay because it's retaining
the console output across
reloads of this browser
page okay so this is looking
at the default form handling
behavior of form elements
now what if we had
another field in
here so let's say
we had another field
making a copy of this
now we're not going to be
naughty and use the same
let's just delete id
because we're not really
we don't really care
about this but let's use a
different name here so this
is color and then we're
going to change the
placeholder to type color thank
you copilot um so let's
see what we're seeing
here now so we have username
and color so if I type
jim actually let's clear
out the console here.
If I type Jim,
and Jim's favorite
color is red, and
we're going to
check his username,
we got, now we got two key
value pairs here. So every
field in the form is going
to be represented in the
query string that gets
sent to a back-end server.
And so the dev server for
this Vite dev server, it's
being hit with this query
string appended to the host
name and port. And if my
backend server wasn't this
Vite dev server, but it
was an actual server that
was going to take this
username and do something with
it, like create a new
identity on a given platform,
well, that server
would be receiving this
information. And that's
how we set up these client
-server applications using
the browser, is by pushing
data to the backend
server using a GET request
or a POST request or
whatever. There's different
types of these requests
that we can define.
All right, so let's go back
and restore our behavior here.
And how do we get that
color? How can we collect
that value? Well,
Copilot's trying to be
really helpful here. and
it's showing me that I
can select that color
input using a selector in
which I provide the the
name is the attribute
that I'm looking for
for an element and
then the color and and
the word color is the
value of that attribute
So we have name equal
color, and I can do a
query selector here.
Okay, let's do one
last thing here.
So this is kind of
interesting because we
have this form variable
that we defined,
and we assigned the form
variable the value of
document.querySelector.
And so we got that, and
that's how we added the
event listener. But what if
I wanted to scope my DOM
lookups, not to the entire
document, but just to
the specific form because
I can't have another
element with the same ID.
If I had a second username
input ID tagged element
further down the DOM, then
I'm pretty sure that this
input would just pick up the
second one that was defined.
I'm pretty sure that's
how query selector works.
Or maybe it's the first
one. I'm not sure.
But don't do that. don't
set up two elements with
the same id you're just
going to confuse yourself
but it's perfectly reasonable
to use different name
different elements that
may have the same attribute
the same name attribute
and the same value
because maybe you have
a one form two forms
on the same web page
and they both need a
color input okay I
defined this form value
constant variable and I
use that to invoke this
addEventListener and
then if I want to look
up values not in the
entire document but scoped
within that form container
I can replace document
here with form and
it will work exactly
like it used to go away
go away I don't want you
um let's add this I'm just
going to do this form color
input dot value okay so
let's see what happens here
so here's our browser and
let's go ahead and clear
out our console and we're
going to type janie and
we're going to type orange
for our color and we're
going to check username okay
so we got a submit event
here and there are it's
printing out hello Janie orange
and we were able to look
up these elements that
were scoped within this
Dom element of form this
container so that's a extremely
useful tool in your browser
apps is to make sure you
don't find things that
you didn't mean to find And
you can do CSS query selector
strings that are scoped
within a given element.
Okay,
we need to wrap this up. I've
been talking a
really long time.
Okay, so we are back to
having prevent default
defined here, okay? and
that's why we no longer need
this let me just clear
this out so if his favorite
color is yellow if I hit
enter we can see that
now we're not seeing that
behavior of the whole
browser reloading we're not
seeing those query parameters
thrown into our url and
leaked to the server
that served this page we're
seeing that we're getting
our console logs here
without even we don't
even need keep log anymore
we can just do this okay
so we're not seeing that
refresh behavior anymore and
there's different means by
which you can get to the
various packages of values
that are in the form. I'm
going to leave that for
another day because we're deep
into this time now. But
the main usefulness of this
example here is just giving
you a little bit of head
start on using the browser
runtime environments
capabilities around HTML forms
attaching a submit handler
to your form so that you
can start doing some of
your tests that you want to
make against the value and
indicate whether it is a
correct value or not okay and
let's say I wanted to do
a simple comparison so say
function check length let's
say we want to make sure
that the username is at
least five characters long.
So if username.length
is less than five,
then we're going
to print an error.
Thank you, Copilot.
You're so helpful.
Okay.
All right.
And we're going to invoke
that check length function
after we've retrieved
that value we don't have
a color input anymore
because I just deleted that
so we're going to do a
check length so we get the
input we get the inputs
value and then we're going
to say hello username and
we're also add in your
username is valid equal and
then I'm going to put in
an invocation of our check
length function
of username okay
and so now we're actually
wiring up some of our
stuff here okay so what
is this gonna do it's not
gonna work how I wanted
it to so let's say george
is a legal name because
it's got six characters
I hit check username and
So what happened here?
Well, we got the value,
the name printed here.
Your username equal
value equal undefined.
Why is it undefined?
Well, it's undefined
because I did not
return a value here.
So we see that this console
didn't run, but what
got returned out of this
function was undefined.
that's the default return
value of a function this
is a super common programming
error is to forget to
put a return value into
our function so what we
want to do is we want to
return a evaluation and
because we don't want to
repeat ourselves we're gonna
say const is valid equal
username but length is
greater than equal to
five okay and if not is
valid we're still going
to print our console, and
then we're going to
return our isValid, okay?
Okay, so we get a username
passed to our function,
and we assign isValid
the Boolean result of
comparing the length of that
string to the constant 5.
We print out a warning
message to the console if
the username is too short
and then we return the value
that we received from
that assignment there okay
and so now we should get
what we wanted to get here
so let's say jim well jim
is too short but jimbo
is perfectly valid okay
so it's sort of the
scaffolding of your html work
and um yeah the assignment
has to be at least four
characters not more than
16 why would there be a
maximum length required
good question no spaces
are allowed in the username
that's just ugly it has to
start with a letter can't
start with a number or
syllable and only numbers
letters and underscores are
allowed and then there's
some little suggestions here
to use this and then we're
going to want to do some
testing so ideally you'll
be exporting the functions
that you define in order
to do these tests and
you're going to import them
into your test and then you
can exercise each function
in the test and make sure
that it is actually um
returning the expected value
okay so how would I export
that value from my app
js well I would just do
something like this so I can
bring this function definition
and I can drop it down
here we already said that
function declarations can
be defined anywhere in the
module this is not currently
exported so we're going
to have to export it we're
going to export our check
length function it is
accessible within our function
due to our hoisting so
let's just verify that we
still have a valid program
here with my changes it's
still working okay and
then if I want to create a
test for this let's go
to my test module I've
been just hacking this up
directly in my oh no I did
actually make a copy of
this so let's go ahead
and grab the starter test
and we're just gonna I'm
gonna leave that test be
because it's a it's got
some good stuff in it and
let's just save as we're
going to call this
username validations okay
and we're going to change
the name of this test we
don't even need this
before each because
what I'm going to do
is I'm going to import
my function which I
called check length
and I don't even need
this I don't need to
render the app at
all because these are
sort of very simple
utility functions and
we're going to make
sure that this function
can validate the
minimum length and
we're going to do an
expect check length
of a three-character
username and we're going to
say we want it to be
return false sometimes
there's a falsity oh yeah
there we go I don't know
if that that may be a
guess to be falsie falsies
the word we want there
okay and then let's add
another actually a lot
of these sometimes you
can put a little thing to
print out but can validate
the minimum like this
is to one more expect
check length of
ABCDE to be truthy.
And let's get rid
of these duplicative
tests. So we don't
really need those. Okay.
And you notice in my editor,
I have a syntax checking
plugin for visual studio
so it's basically this is
just showing that the read
file sync is being imported
but it's not being used nor
is the before each being
used that's kind of dimmed
out and let's go ahead and
run our test suite now so
let's go into cd projects
So I should look.
three.
Cross my fingers.
It's failing. Okay. Let's see.
Um, expect app dot text
content to be at this, this
starter test is annoying
because it's always going to
break once we make any change
to the method. So let's
see. Render starter message
can query by selector
text content.
Let's just delete this.
Actually, we can just do this.
It renders.
We'll change this
to renders the form.
And let's say that we want
the text content to match.
And what did we put
in our markup here?
Well, it's got the
word username in it.
Let's just make sure
that the word username
ended up somewhere in that
text content property.
Happy.
Awesome. Okay.
All right. So, yeah,
that's real quick.
Yeah, the recommendation
is not to try to
phish values out of the DOM
and use a test to actually
type information into
the text field. Now, that
may be a reasonable test
to write at some point in a
more complicated web app,
but in this case, we just
want to kind of lean on the
basic form behavior that
we can quickly evaluate
by monkey testing our
developer preview session
that Vite is rendering to us.
But you know, this
username validation,
you know,
try to create a comprehensive
set of tests that cover
all of the requirements of
our validation rules and
make sure that you're testing
both the positive case
that a valid value passes
but also the negative case
that an invalid value does
not pass and if you want to
make it even cooler you can
put in a little indicator
instead of logging
it to the console you
might put a little
indicator in your browser
rendering that actually
shows the result of the
validations that might be
a cool thing to do okay
all right so and that
would be something
that you're going to
wire up here okay so
instead of reporting
our results let's
go ahead and create
a wrapper function to
export function check all
and we definitely
are going to need to
pass the username to
it and we're gonna
well right now all
we care about is
the check length
let's return an object
Okay.
So what we want is if
any of these evaluate
to false, then we're
going to return false.
so let's do a const
length check equal check
length of username
and let's just do this
and we'll return a object
with that result in
it so we can pass that
sort of the fully fledged
expression of all
of the different
return values okay in an object
but we might want to
return a falsie result
if any of the values
failed to validate
but I'm going to leave
that up to you okay so we
have length as our first
value here our test okay
and we can see that
if we do a const
validations equal
check all of username
and then we do a
uh console.log and
we're just going to
do the validations
and that's going to print
out our lovely object
okay it doesn't like something
about log template
validations does
anybody see my syntax
error here hello username
your username is valid
equal I think there's
Just an extra parenthesis
there somewhere,
console.log.
Sometimes if you're
running into syntax
errors, you can just
delete some code
and it looks like it is that
console that it doesn't like.
Extra parenthesis there, okay?
And what if we wanted to
put in a little field?
And we're just gonna put
that in the bottom here.
div is id equal result
and we're going to keep
that empty for now
because we don't have any
information in it and
let's say if our main
event listener go away
go away copilot I'm going
to say that the result
we're grabbing the
result value and we're
going to set the constant
and here is the
validations.length. Your
username is of correct
length equal validations.
Hello,
Bo, your username is of
correct length equals false.
But if I call it Bobby,
hello, Bo,
hello, Bobby, your username
is correct length equals true.
All right, so there's
a lot you can do
here. You can make
this look really cool,
and I will leave
that up to you.
and um you know um yeah I
hope you have some fun with
this thing you can um make
it really cool all right
I'll see you guys next week
thanks for listening this
far and um yeah reach out
if you need any help cheers